Guide to the Mina Curtiss Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mina Curtiss Collection
1910-1945
MS 1206
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes)
The original accession consists of original and typed copies of letters sent home by American servicemen from various training camps in the United States and from overseas campaigns during World War II, many of which Mina Curtiss used for her 1944 book, Letters Home. The addition consists of Henry T. Curtiss papers and photographs. There are a diary and book relating to Curtiss's 1910 trip to Europe on the S.S. Arabic, which included stops in the British Isles, Holland, Germany, Venice, Scutari and Dalmatia; a volume of letters and photographs sent by members of the Scroll and Key Society to one another from 1920-1923, with reminiscences about Curtiss after his death in 1928; and eight large photographs of Curtiss alone and with friends, circa 1910.
Curtiss, Mina Kirstein, 1896-1985
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mina Curtiss. Gift of Lincoln Kirstein and the Estate of George Kirstein, 1986.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Mina Kirstein Curtiss was born on October 13, 1896, in Boston, Massachusetts. She graduated from Smith College in 1918, received a M.A. in English from Columbia University in 1920, and returned to Smith, where she was an associate professor until 1934. She was a research assistant for the Mercury Theater from 1935 to 1938, and she worked for the Office of War Information during World War II. She taught at Smith from 1940 to 1941. In 1942, Curtiss wrote and produced a local radio program in Des Moines, Iowa, in which she featured Iowa soldiers' letters home, and interviews with their families. The response inspired her to expand the project and incorporate letters of servicemen from all over the country, and in 1944 she published an anthology of enlisted men's Letters Home. During the next decades, Curtiss spent much time in France, and later Russia. She was the author of many publications, and received the Legion of Honor from the French government for her books on Marcel Proust and Georges Bizet. She married Henry ("Harry") Tomlinson Curtiss on June 1, 1926. Curtiss died on November 1, 1985.
Scope and Contents
The original accession consists of original and typed copies of letters sent home by American servicemen from various training camps in the United States and from overseas campaigns during World War II, many of which Mina Curtiss used for her 1944 book, Letters Home. The addition consists of Henry T. Curtiss papers and photographs. There are a diary and book relating to Curtiss's 1910 trip to Europe on the S.S. Arabic, which included stops in the British Isles, Holland, Germany, Venice, Scutari and Dalmatia; a volume of letters and photographs sent by members of the Scroll and Key Society to one another from 1920-1923, with reminiscences about Curtiss after his death in 1928; and eight large photographs of Curtiss alone and with friends, circa 1910.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
College students -- Connecticut -- 20th Century; Ocean travel -- 20th Century; Travelers; Voyages and travels -- 20th Century; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; Europe -- Description and travel -- 20th Century; Travel journals; Authors; Clement, Stephen Merrell, 1887-1943; Curtiss, Henry Tomlinson, 1888-1928; Curtiss, Mina Kirstein, 1896-1985; Platt, Joseph Curtis, 1887-1950; Roome, Reginald, 1888-1949; Williams, Earl Trumbull, 1888-1918; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1910; Yale University -- Students -- 20th Century
- Original Accession: Military Letters, 1939-1945
  - Alaska and Aleutians, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "At Sea", 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Australia, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Australia and New Zealand, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Canal Zone, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chile, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - China, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Egypt and Middle East, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - England, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - England - English Allied Forces, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fiji Islands, Midway, Wake, Saipan, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - France, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Germany, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Guadalcanal and the Solomons, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hawaii, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - India, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ireland, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Italy, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Japan, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - New Caledonia, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - New Guinea, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - New Guinea, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - North Africa, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 27-30)
  - North Africa, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - Noumea, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Okinawa, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Philippine Islands, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Saipan, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Scotland, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - South Pacific, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Tonga, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - United States
    - Air Force, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Army, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 41-43)
    - Hospitals, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Military government, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Marines, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Navy, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Paratroops (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Quartermaster Corps, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Signal Corps, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Ski troops, Undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Additional Material, 1910-1928; Accession 1987-M-0010
  Scope and Contents
  This addition to the Mina Curtiss Collection consists of journals, letters, and photographs belonging to her husband, Henry T. Curtiss. Items include a diary kept by Curtiss during a 1910 trip to Europe with Yale classmates and fellow Scroll and Key Society members S. Merrell Clement, Jr., J. Curtis Platt, Reginald Roome, and Earl T. Williams. The diary describes the group's travels on the S. S. Arabic to the British Isles, Holland, Germany, Venice, Scutari and Dalmatia. There is also a leather binder of photographs and letters circulated annually among Scroll and Key Society members. The inside cover contains a photographic negative of Henry Curtiss and a friend on horseback. The majority of the letters, from 1920 to 1923, are arranged first by author and then by date. Curtiss's own letters are near the end of this group, and a later photograph of him outside his Ashfield home is found after his entries. The final group of letters, from 1927 to 1928, includes reminiscences about Curtiss after his death. Related to these two volumes is the book Diary of a Trip Abroad in the Summer of 1910, by Earl Trumbull Williams. Published after Williams' early death, this book serves as a companion volume to Henry Curtiss's account of the trip. There are also eight large photographs of Curtiss alone and with friends, circa 1910. Five of the photos are card-mounted and numbered, and depict various scenes of Curtiss and classmates at the beach, at school, in Europe, and on a ship. The other three photos have been captioned, presumably by Mina Curtiss, and depict a "Keys wedding"; Curtiss with his dogs outside his Ashfield home; and Curtiss with Bobby Jones, Jack Davidson, and Fred Kennedy.
  - "A Diary of a Trip to Europe The Summer of 1910" [manuscript journal], 1910 July 2-September 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs and letters of Scroll and Key Society alumni from Yale College Class of 1910, 1920-1923, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diary of a Trip Abroad in the Summer of 1910 by Earl Trumbull Williams, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Circa 1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)